{
  "filename": "2018-2019-HS-History-Bowl-Round-1-A-Set_formattedText.txt",
  "questions": [
    {
      "number": "1.2",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "KGB (or Komitet Gosudarstvennoy Bezopasnosti; accept Committee for StateSecurity)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "As part of Operation PANDORA, this organization tried to stir up anti-Semitism by mailing outracist fake pamphlets of right-wing Jewish organizations to civil rights organizations. This organization,which often collaborated with GRU, was led by Vladimir Kryuchkov, who helped plan an August 1991coup. During the fall of the Berlin Wall, thousands of this organization’s files were burned by its officers,including Vladimir Putin. For ten points, name this Soviet intelligence agency."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.3",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Boston",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "In 1894, kids accidentally started a fire under the stands in this city’s South End Grounds duringa baseball game; the stadium and over 100 buildings were destroyed in the ensuing Great RoxburyFire. This city lost over 60 acres worth of buildings in 12 hours after a warehouse on Kingston Streetcaught fire in 1872; that event was commemorated by its resident poet, Oliver Wendell Holmes Senior. In1919, 21 people died after a storage tank burst and released a flood of molasses in, for ten points, whatMassachusetts city?"
    },
    {
      "number": "1.4",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Carl von Clausewitz",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This man’s philosophy notably clashed with that of his contemporary, Antoine-Henri Jomini. Oneof this thinker’s students applied his philosophy at the Battle of Sedan; that student was Helmuth vonMoltke. This man defined war as “the continuation of politics by other means,” and he described theconfusion during “the fog of war” in his most famous work. For ten points, name this distinguished 19thcentury Prussian military strategist who wrote On War."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.5",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "University of Pennsylvania (accept UPenn; do not accept Penn State)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "A student of this university named Sadie Tanner Mossell Alexander was the first African Americanwoman to receive a Ph.D. A machine known as the “Giant Brain” was created at this university tocalculate artillery firing tables; that early computer was ENIAC. The oldest medical school created inAmerica is this university’s Perelman School, and it is also home to the first school of business, whichis named after Joseph Wharton. For ten points, name this university founded by Benjamin Franklin inPhiladelphia."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.6",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Vincent (Willem) van GoghPage 1NHBB A-Set Bowl 2018-2019 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This artist painted his friend Adrianus Jacobus Zuyderland dressed in blue with his head in his handsin At Eternity’s Gate, which shares its name with a 2018 film about this man. A landscape painting bythis artist depicts a cypress tree and a crescent moon over the town of Saint-Remy. This artist of ThePotato Eaters was hospitalized in Arles after injuring himself with a razor in 1888. For ten points, namethis Dutch artist of Starry Night and Self Portrait with Bandaged Ear."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.7",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Battle of Antietam",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Prior to this battle, one side lost control of the Crampton and Turner passes during the Battle ofSouth Mountain, nearly leading them to terminate their campaign. The losing side in this battle washampered when Special Order 191 was discovered, wrapped in cigars, by the enemy. After a costly seizureof the Bloody Lane, George McClellan failed to press his advantage at this battle, leading Lincoln toreplace him with Ambrose Burnside. For ten points, name this 1862 Maryland battle, the bloodiest singleday of the Civil War."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.8",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "David Ben-Gurion",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This man returned to power after the scandal of the Lavon Affair, a botched false-flag bombingoperation. Ahdut HaAvoda was founded by this man, who ordered the formation of Unit 101 andorganized a massive airlift in Operation Magic Carpet as Prime Minister. During his second term, thisman launched an invasion of Egypt, precipitating the Suez Crisis. For ten points, name this first primeminister of Israel."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.9",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Cardinal Jules Mazarin",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This man rose to power after scheming with the Comte de Chevigny [comt de sheh-vi-nee] to removeFranc¸ois de Noyers [fran-swah de no-yay]. The League of the Rhine was formed by this man to limitAustrian power. This man concluded a war with Spain through the Treaty of the Pyrenees. This advisorbarely survived a coup during the Fronde. For ten points, name this cardinal who acted as minister forLouis XIII and regent for Louis XIV."
    },
    {
      "number": "1.10",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "Watergate scandal",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "In a series of documents related to this scandal, William Rehnquist was referred to as “Renchburg;”the existence of those documents was publicly revealed by Alexander Butterfield. John Mitchell served19 months in prison for his role in this scandal, which included Robert Bork’s agreement to fire specialprosecutor Archibald Cox during the Saturday Night Massacre. The “Smoking Gun” tape was a key pieceof evidence in, for ten points, what scandal that ended with Richard Nixon’s resignation?"
    },
    {
      "number": "1.11",
      "quarter": 1,
      "answer": "CyprusPage 2NHBB A-Set Bowl 2018-2019 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "On this island, Marco Bragadin was infamously flayed alive after leading a heroic defense ofFamagusta to delay the Ottoman Empire prior to Lepanto. Joan of England was captured by thisisland’s ruler Isaac Komnenos, prompting Richard I to invade it. This country’s modern Enosis movementprompted Operation Atilla, an invasion that helped extend this country’s Green Line of demarcation. Forten points, name this island country divided between Turkish and Greek zones."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.1",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Pullman Strike",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "After this event, William Graham was criticized for memorializing members of the 5th Artillery whowere killed on a dynamite-laced bridge while en route to stop this event. A rally to drum up support forthis event was held at Blue Island, and it occurred despite an injunction from Richard Olney. When thisevent was deemed to interfere with federal mail, Grover Cleveland stepped in to end it. For ten points,name this 1894 Chicago strike against a namesake railway company."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.1.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Eugene V. Debs",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "This labor leader helped lead the Pullman Strike, years before he ran as a Socialist Partycandidate for President from a jail cell."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.2",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "amaZulu people",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This ethnic group was involved in the Bambatha Rebellion in 1907, and it won a major militaryvictory in 1879 after a solar eclipse appeared over the battlefield. This ethnic group was defeated at theBattle of Blood River, and this ethnic group’s king, Cetshwayo, was defeated at the Battle of Rorke’sDrift. For ten points, name this ethnic group, the victors at the Battle of Isandlwana, who ruled an empirein southern Africa until they were conquered by the British."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.2.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Shaka Zulu (or Shaka kaSenzangakhona)",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "This Zulu king revamped their military procedures and died in 1828, well before the Britishconquest."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.3",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Las Vegas",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This city failed to annex a section of neighboring land after the Mafia organized it into anunincorporated town called Paradise. In 2010, a stock image of a landmark in this city was accidentallyused for a Forever Stamp; that half-size replica of the Statue of Liberty stands outside the New York-NewYork Hotel. The construction of the Hoover Dam fueled the early growth of, for ten points, what mostpopulous city in Nevada, a gambling resort town?"
    },
    {
      "number": "2.3.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Howard HughesPage 3NHBB A-Set Bowl 2018-2019 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "This American business tycoon purchased the Desert Inn in Las Vegas after refusing to leaveone of its rooms. This famously reclusive man designed the Spruce Goose, a wooden plane."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.4",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Marcus Licinius Crassus",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This man befriended the Vestal Virgin Licinia to take her land. This man died in a skirmish afterhis assistant Octavius awkwardly tried to stop him from taking part in a peace negotiation. This manbecame wealthy by running a bucket brigade that would not help douse fires until homeowners paid him. This man’s victory at the Battle of the Siler River ended a slave revolt. A Parthian army killed this manand legendarily poured molten gold in the mouth of his corpse. For ten points, name this wealthy Romanwho put down Spartacus’ revolt and formed the First Triumvirate with Julius Caesar and Pompey."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.4.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Appian Way (or Via Appia)",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "After Spartacus’ revolt was put down, Crassus ordered the crucifixion of six thousand slavesalong this road from Rome to Brindisium."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.5",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Baby Boomers",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "The phrase “pig in the python” titled a cultural history of this group, which was collectively namedTime Person of the Year in 1966. Reduced adult supervision led this group’s successor to be called the“latchkey generation”. Lower mortgage requirements and the G.I. bill contributed to the rise of, for tenpoints, what American generation that was succeeded by Generation X and was born after World War II?"
    },
    {
      "number": "2.5.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Great Society",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "The aging curve of the Baby Boomers is often cited as a financial threat to Medicare, which wasintroduced as part of this set of domestic policies by Lyndon Johnson in 1964."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.6",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Stonehenge",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This site was once believed to have been imported from Africa for use in healing, then transportedfrom Mount Killaraus after a long battle. In 1915, this site was sold for 6000 pounds to Cecil Chubbs, whothen donated it. This site is surrounded by “aubrey holes” speculated to have once contained bluestones;earlier historians speculated this site was a center of Druidic worship. For ten points, name this prehistoricsite near Salisbury consisting of standing rocks."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.6.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "igneous rockPage 4NHBB A-Set Bowl 2018-2019 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "Most of the bluestones of Stonehenge are made of dolerite, which is this type of rock. Ireland’sGiant’s Causeway is made of thousands of columns of basalt, another example of this type of rock."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.7",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Federal Reserve (System)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This institution was created after Charles Lindbergh, Sr. helped inspire the creation of the PujoCommittee. James Reed’s decisive vote helped create this institution, resulting in his home state ofMissouri being granted two of its 12 major branches. This agency was created by a bill introduced byRobert Owen and Carter Glass, each of whom chaired a congressional Banking and Currency Committee. A 1913 act created, for ten points, what central banking system of the US?"
    },
    {
      "number": "2.7.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Jerome Powell",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "This man succeeded Janet Yellen as chair of the Federal Reserve in 2018, despite not having aPhD in Economics."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.8",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Yuri Alekseyevich Gagarin",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "At a 1993 auction, a dummy named Ivan that was meant to test conditions prior to this man’s mostfamous undertaking sold for nearly $200,000. A cedar tree inspired the most famous callsign of this man,who exclaimed “Poyekhali! ” In 1968, this man died while flying a MiG-15 after an air traffic controllermisreported the weather, according to declassified files. After a mission of less than two hours in 1961,this man parachuted back to Earth. For ten points, name this cosmonaut who, aboard Vostok 1, becamethe first man in space."
    },
    {
      "number": "2.8.B",
      "quarter": 2,
      "answer": "Soyuz (accept Soyuz 1)",
      "is_bonus": true,
      "question": "In 1967, Gagarin was the backup pilot for the first manned flight of this Soviet spacecraft, whichled to the first in-flight death in spaceflight history. This series of spacecraft is still in use by the Russianspace program."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.1",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Osama bin Laden",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Leader of al-Qaeda who was killed in Pakistan in 2011."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.2",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "World Trade Center (or WTC; accept Twin Towers)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Building complex in New York that was destroyed on 9/11."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.3",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Guantanamo Bay",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "American detention camp in Cuba where terrorists have been interrogated."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.4",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Khalid Sheikh Mohammed (accept KSM)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Member of al-Qaeda who was the “architect” of 9/11 and the 2002 Bali nightclub bombing; he wascaptured in 2003."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.5",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "waterboarding",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Form of water-based torture used by the US on members of al-Qaeda, including that 9/11 architect."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.6",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "anthrax",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Bio-toxin that was mailed to multiple news outlets and political figures in 2001."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.7",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "USS Cole",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "American naval destroyer that was attacked by suicide bombers while in port in Yemen in 2000."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.8",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Richard ReidPage 6NHBB A-Set Bowl 2018-2019 Bowl Round 1European FieldsName the...",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Al-Qaeda operative who attempted to light plastic explosives in his shoe on a plane in December2001."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.9",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Battle of Bosworth Field",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Decisive August 1485 battle of the Wars of the Roses."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.10",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Henry VIII [8]",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "English king who met Francis I at the Field of the Cloth of Gold and married six times."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.11",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Attila the Hun",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Leader of the Huns who was defeated at the Catalaunian Fields in the Battle of Chalons [sha-lone]."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.12",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "crop rotation (accept three-field system)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Farming practice of planting fields of wheat, then beans, then nothing, to help replenish the soil."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.13",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "World War I",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "War in which the poem “In Flanders Fields” was written after the Battle of Ypres [eep]."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.14",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Elysian Fields (accept Elysium)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Paradise of Greek myth where heroes not sent to Hades were sent."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.15",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Kosovo (accept Battle of Kosovo Polje)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Former Serbian territory where a 1389 battle of the Field of Blackbirds took place."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.16",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Manchester (do not accept Peterloo Massacre)Page 7NHBB A-Set Bowl 2018-2019 Bowl Round 1Religious CitiesName the...",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "English city where an 1819 massacre took place in St. Peter’s Field."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.17",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Jerusalem",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "City that is home to the Temple Mount and the Dome of the Rock, the holiest city of Christianityand Judaism."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.18",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Mecca",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Holiest city of Islam, the destination of the hajj."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.19",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Buddhism",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Religion founded by Siddhartha Gautama, who gave his first sermon at Sarnath near Varanasi."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.20",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Nazareth",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Hometown of Jesus in the New Testament and capital of the Crusader-era Principality of Galilee."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.21",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Tibet",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Plateau region claimed by China where Buddhists built monasteries in Lhasa."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.22",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Kyoto",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Japanese city home to hundreds of Buddhist temples, including the Temple of the Golden Pavilion."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.23",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "Haifa",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "City where the Shrine of the Bab, part of the Baha’i World Center, was built on Mount Carmel in1891."
    },
    {
      "number": "3.24",
      "quarter": 3,
      "answer": "HeliopolisPage 8NHBB A-Set Bowl 2018-2019 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Ancient Egyptian city, now a suburb of Cairo, where the sun god Atum was worshipped."
    },
    {
      "number": "4.2",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Qin [chin] Dynasty",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This dynasty’s general Meng Tian defeated the Xiongnu [shee-ong-nu]. An attempt toassassinate a ruler of this dynasty involved putting lead at the end of a lute. This dynasty,whose chancellor (+) Li Si instituted Legalist policies, was led by a man who supposedlydrank an “elixir of life” that was just mercury. This dynasty, which followed the (*) WarringStates Period, was replaced by the Han Dynasty. A terracotta army was built for a ruler of, for ten points,what dynasty in which the Great Wall was built under the rule of Shi Huangdi?"
    },
    {
      "number": "4.3",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Mozart’s Requiem mass in D minor (prompt on mass)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This piece was commissioned for the price of 100 ducats, half paid in advance. Composition of this piece was delayed by time spent finishing La Clemenza di Tito and DieZauberfloete. The figured bass line was all that was (+) finished for some later movementsof this piece, most of which was completed by Franz Sussmayr. Constanze, the wife ofthis work’s composer, tried to keep its unfinished nature a secret after the (*) death of itscomposer in 1791. For ten points, name this musical piece that Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart believed hewas composing for his own funeral."
    },
    {
      "number": "4.4",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Conservative and Unionist Party",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "One leader of this political party tried to restore order with his “Back to Basics”campaign, which backfired after many of his ministers were caught in extramarital affairs. Another leader of this political party lost power in 1974 to a minority-power government ledby (+) Harold Wilson. Yet another leader of this party conducted a namesake program ofprivatizing government companies, was the target of the (*) Brighton Hotel bombing, and wasnicknamed “the Iron Lady”. Margaret Thatcher belonged to, for ten points, what British political party?"
    },
    {
      "number": "4.5",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Viet Cong (or National Liberation Front)Page 9NHBB A-Set Bowl 2018-2019 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "Members of this irregular fighting force often used the “one slow, four quick” doctrine. Eddie Adams photographed a captain in this group who had recently killed a LieutenantColonel and his family; in that photo, the member of this group is wearing a flannel shirtand (+) shot at point blank range by General Nguyen Loan [when loan]. This group ledmultiple attacks in January (*) 1968, striking the city of Hue [hway] and breaching the U.S. embassyin Saigon. For ten points, name this guerrilla fighting group that fought against the U.S. and SouthVietnam during the Tet Offensive."
    },
    {
      "number": "4.6",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "ancient library (accept Library of Alexandria; accept Library of Ashurbanipal after hisname is mentioned)",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "While Aristophanes of Byzantium led one of these facilities, he invented the diacriticalmarks used in the Greek language; Aristarchus of Samothrace later led that one of thesefacilities. When one of these facilities was excavated in (+) Ashurbanipal’s palace, itsdiscoveries were mixed with tablets found in Sennacherib’s palace, rendering the truediscovery location of the (*) Epic of Gilgamesh a mystery. For ten points, name this type of locationthat Julius Caesar burned in Alexandria, causing the loss of thousands of papyrus scrolls and theireducational contents."
    },
    {
      "number": "4.7",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "Louisiana Purchase",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "The president who authorized this agreement wrote a letter outlining his diplomaticstrategy to Governor James Gerrard of Kentucky. Fran¸cois de Barb´e-Marbois [bar-baymar-bwah] was a key negotiator of this agreement, which arose after an (+) insurrectionon Saint Domingue [sahn doh-meeng]. Talleyrand objected to this plan, which resulted inthe (*) Lewis and Clark Expedition surveying its central land area. The size of the United States wasdoubled by, for ten points, what 1803 purchase of French land under Thomas Jefferson?"
    },
    {
      "number": "4.8",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "seven",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "The weekly Torah reading is divided into this many aliyahs. In the first part of the bookof Revelation, the author writes letters to this many churches in Asia Minor. Jericho’s (+)walls fell after this many days of marching, and King David had this many brothers. ThePassover feast lasts this many days, and this is the number of (*) lamps on the Temple ofJerusalem’s menorah. For ten points, give this number of the day God rested in the first Genesis narrative,which is also the number of deadly sins."
    },
    {
      "number": "4.9",
      "quarter": 4,
      "answer": "CharlemagnePage 10NHBB A-Set Bowl 2018-2019 Bowl Round 1",
      "is_bonus": false,
      "question": "This man’s deformed son was sent to the monastery of Pru¨m after his plot to overthrowthis man was discovered. This man’s mother Bertrada assisted him in his struggle againsthis brother, and he divorced his (+) Lombard wife Desiderata before conquering Italy. Thisruler, who put down the Great Saxon Revolt after converting them to Christianity, hadhis forces defeated at the Battle of (*) Roncevaux Pass, the source of the Song of Roland. For tenpoints, name this Frankish king crowned Emperor of the Romans on Christmas Day 800."
    }
  ],
  "categories": ["Modern Terrorism", "European Fields", "Religious Cities"]

}